Welcome to lecture thirty-six of the course
on High Performance Computing. In previous
two lectures, we have started looking at the
file system which is an important part of
the software side of any computer system,
particularly if your programs are dealing
with data, there must survive beyond the execution
time of your program.
This is a new kind of data, in the sense that,
until now, when we talked about the data of
a program, we were referring to data that
was created and used by the program for parts
of the execution time of the program, where
as, in reality, there could be situations
where you want the data to survive beyond
the execution time of the program; in which
case, files and the file system become important.
Now, we were looking at some of the design
issues, the mechanisms that are taken into
account by people who design operating systems,
in designing the file system part of the operating
system. And one of the...I have talked about
three main issues we were going to discuss-one,
relating to disk block management; the management
of the disk which is the important persistent
on nonvolatile secondary storage device, which
we are taking into account in discussing file
systems. And we saw that, the prevalent mechanism
that is used for managing the disk in terms
of allocating disk blocks to files is something
known as indexed allocation; in which, an
array of disk block addresses is associated
with the each file. The first disk block address
would refer to the first disk block containing
the data pertaining to this file. The subsequent
data and the file would be contained in the
subsequent disk block, as mentioned in the
index.
Now, it is important in designing such a mechanism,
that one takes into account, the frequently
occurring kinds of access patterns to files.
In addition to this, one must take into account,
the need for files should be able to grow
and shrink, potentially to fairly large sizes.
And in addition, the designer of the file
system must ensure that the size of the index
of the data structure that is used to keep
track of a file, should not be too large.
And among the various alternatives that we
looked at, this form of indexed allocation,
as used in Unix or Linux systems was found
to be the best. So, in short, there are, in
this particular example, I am showing you
a index or index node or I node for short,
which contains just twelve disk block addresses,
but could actually allow you to represent
a file which is many gigabytes in size due
to the use of not only in direction, but double
indirection. In other words, not just indicating
the addresses of the disk blocks containing
the data of the file, but in addition, using
disk blocks to contain the disk block addresses
of subsequent blocks, pertaining to the file.
And doing this not only at one level of indirection,
but at two or may be even three levels of
in indirection to allow for fairly large files,
as I said, up to gigabytes in size with assuming
that the size of a single disk block or sector
is 1 kilobyte even if there are only twelve
indices at twelve addresses included in the
index.
Now, we will move on to the second file system
design issue, in other words, name management.
Recall that, we understand a file to be a
named sequence of data on a secondary storage
device, such as a disk.
So, the management of the names of the files
is important. The question of how can a user
refer to a file and how will the operating
system associate the correct name with a correct
collection of disk blocks, in order to provide
the data that the user actually requires.
Now, the issues in name management, first
of all, we have to have a clear understanding
of how a user can refer to a file. So, how
were the names constructed? And given a name,
how does the operating system locate the file
on the disk and subsequently read the associated
disk blocks to provide data as requested by
the program in execution?
Now, the primary structure which is used by
operating systems today, for name management
is something known as a directory. And the
directory is a mapping between file names
and the corresponding file descriptors. You
will recall that, I had used the term file
descriptor in the previous lecture, to refer
to, in the day, operating system data structure
that is used keep track of which disk blocks
correspond to a particular file.
So, corresponding to any one file, they would
be one file descriptor, which would contain
the information regarding the various disk
blocks associated with that file, along with
possibly other information. But what we are
learning today is that, the directory or the
mapping between the names and the actual descriptors
could be maintained, not within the file descriptor,
but rather in a separate structure called
a directory.
In other words, it is not typically the case
that the name is part of the file descriptor.
As we saw in the previous class, the information
in the file descriptor was typically something
like the index, in other words, the specification
of which disk blocks contain the data associated
with this file. And there could be other information
as we are shortly going to see. So, in short,
then the mechanism for name management, the
primary mechanism for name management is the
directory and mapping between file names and
file descriptors. So, the user can refer to
a file by a name, the operating system can
refer to that name within the corresponding
directory and hence get the file descriptor
using which, the disk blocks of the file can
be accessed.
Now, the issue which arises now is, how could
the operating system maintain this directory
information efficiently. Now, one possibility
which you could immediately think of is that,
the operating system could maintain a single
directory for the entire disk. So, for each
of the disks which is, which contains files,
there could be a directory and that directory
could contain, for each of the files on that
disk, the name and the corresponding file
descriptor. And you could immediately see
that, this is somewhat restrictive in that,
if there is only one directory for the entire
disk, then there has to be a unique name for
every file on the disk and therefore, it would
have to be ensured that, no two files have
the same name. So, this may not sound like
much of a problem, but if you think about
it a little bit, this could be a severe problem.
Imagine, there is a situation where there
is a very large disk. Let say, 300 or 500
gigabytes in size. Such a disk could contain
many thousands of files. And the files may
potentially be owned by different users. Now,
if it is required that each user makes up
unique name across the entire file system
for each of his files, and you will see that,
this would end up being a problem. Every time
that I wanted to create a name for a file
that I intend to use, I would first have to,
in some sense, ensure that this name had not
been used before by anyone else, any of the
user or in fact, in fact, in fact, myself,
including myself for other files on the same
file system.
So, this is definitely constrained that be
too much to cooperate. So, for example, I
mean, we have talked about many times about
a C program called program dot c. And if the
situation was one way, the operating system
was maintaining a single directory for the
entire disk, then this what imply that, there
could be only one file called program dot
c in the entire system among all the users
on the system. There could be only one file
called program dot c and very clearly this
would be far too restrictive.
Now, there may be certain situations where
you could have seen this as not being too
much of a problem. For example, let suppose
that it is a situation where there is only
one user. Simple example of that is a personal
computer. There may only be the one user,
in fact, on certain early personal computers,
this kind of a directory may have been adequate.
But today, very clearly we must understand
that, even on a personal computer, there could
be many users and this is too much of a restriction
which leads us to the second possibility.
Rather than maintaining a single directory
for all the files on the disk, the operating
system could maintain a separate directory
for each user.
So, if there are ten users on a system, there
could be ten directories, one for each of
the users. And the user of the directory of
a given user will contain all the files, would
contain information about the mapping between
names and descriptors for all the files created
and used by that particular user. Now, once
again, we need to, we understand now that,
under this mechanism, there could actually
be many files called program dot c on a particular
disk. Each user could now have a file called
program dot c. And when a program which I
have written, tries to open a file called
program dot c, the operating system would
know that, it has to look for the mapping
information relating to program dot c in the
directory associated with me, as a user. You
will recall that, we understand that the operating
system maintain or differentiates between
users by having a different user ID for every
user.
So, the user that, the directory associated
with my user ID is one that would be refer
to, when my program tries to open a file called
program dot c. Now, you may imagine that,
this too could be a little bit restrictive.
Because now, while every user on the system
could have their own file called program dot
c, there could only be, as far as I am concerned,
as myself being one user, I could only have
one file by a given name. So, I would have
to have unique names for all the files which
I create. And this is the simple example of
how this might not might be a problem.
Now, it might be the case. I would be happy
to have only one file called program dot c,
but I may want to have many files called README
.And those of you who have done programming
or have written documentation may have made
use of the file name README. You will put
a lot of information relating to a particular
project that you have done, a particular assignment
that you worked with or something like that,
into a file called README.
And hence if you have only one directory for
you as a user, then there could be only one
file called README and this in turn, might
be a constraint. Many of you are students,
you may be taking multiple, many courses and
in each course, you may have many programming
assignments to do and typically may want to
have many files which actually have the same
name such as README or even program dot c.
For each of the assignments and each of the
courses that you do, if you want to have the
same name for the file, program dot c, there
should still be possible.
In other words, many different files, because
there is one file for each of the different
programs that you wrote, but you may want
to call each of the files, program dot c .This
may not be a good habit in general, because
could lead to confusion. But it should not
be ruled out by the directory mechanism of
the computer system. And possibly, the need
for multiple files called README would be
a more appealing kind of an example.
Hence we need to look beyond a single directory
for the whole disk and potentially even beyond
a single directory for each user to something
which will allow users to have multiple files
of the same name. And what this leads to is
a much more general idea; the idea of the
operating system actually maintaining a somewhat
complicated structure for directories, and
I will describe it as, what we have come to
is, a Unix or a Linux type idea. Rather than
maintaining a single directory across the
entire disk or a single directory for each
user, the operating system maintains a tree
structured hierarchy of directories. And remove
the word single from there. A tree structured
hierarchy of directories. In other words,
not a single directory even for users, but
a hierarchy of directories.
We have seen the word hierarchy before, and
we understood that whenever the word hierarchy
was used, we were referring to some kind of
a multileveled structure. And hence we are
talking here about something more complicated
than either of the earlier to, and must therefore
be much more general and allow for much more
aggressive kinds of names to be used, such
as, many files called program dot c; even
for a given user.We first need to understand
what a tree is. We have not seen this word
before in this course, but as I had mentioned,
the idea of this tree structured hierarchy
of directories is what one finds in Unix and
Linux systems today.
So, what then is a tree. To properly understand
what a tree structured directory hierarchy
is, we need to understand what a tree is.
The other terms we have seen before. Now,
tree should be viewed as being a kind of a
data structure and you will recall that, we
have seen other data structures. The data
structures that we have seen so far, were
things like the stack, we have seen other
data structures too.
We saw the idea of the list; link list as
being a data structure and so on. So, the
tree is to be viewed as being another kind
of a data structure or collection of data
and the corresponding operations on the data.
Now, typically when you think of a tree, you
think of the tree in nature and this is a
diagram sort of like a tree in nature. This
is the bottom part, the trunk of the tree.
Then, these are the branches of the tree and
leaves all over the tree. So, the diagram
that I have drawn is one, which corresponds
to the picture of tree that you have, when
you think about nature. But more specifically,
what we need to understand from this diagram
is that, this is a structure which may get
its name from the similarity, from the parent
similarity to the tree in nature. But very
clearly, it is showing some structure that
we need to understand better. So, in terms
of some terminology, you will notice that
I have used two structures in creating this;
two kinds of objects in creating this tree
in this drawing.
First, there are the brown circles and there
are the arrowed, I am sorry, the lines, the
directed lines are arrows. And in general,
you could talk of the brown circles as the
nodes or the vertices of the tree. The singular
of the vertices is vertex. So, I use the word
vertex or node. Still, a tree is made up of
nodes or vertices and the nodes or vertices,
these are synonyms, I will use the word node
from now on. So, the nodes of the tree are
connected to each other by these directed
arrows, by these direct lines which are called
edges. So, we will talk about the nodes and
the edges of a tree.
Now, the thing to note is that, a particular
edge goes from one node to another node. For
example, this particular edge goes from the
node at the bottom to the node just above
it on the right side, and the terminology
which we will use is to talk about an edge
going from a parent to a child node.
So, in this particular example, as far as
this edge is concerned, I would refer to the
edge of the node at the bottom as the parent
of the node to which the arrow points. So,
the tree is describing this parent-child relationship
between nodes.
Notice that, a single parent can have multiple
children. For example, the node at the bottom
has three children and there could be some
nodes which do not have any children. For
example, this node over here, does not have
any children.
So, they are certain properties associated
with the tree. But the tree is showing us
some kind of hierarchy and the hierarchy that
is shown here, relates very much to the kinds
of hierarchies we talked about before; you
could view this tree as being capable of describing
a business hierarchy, for example, this could
be the CEO, this could be the three vice-presidents
and so on. So, in some sense, the structure
of the trees, not something that we are that
the similar unfamiliar with. Now, in sense
of further terminology, one property of the
tree is that the tree has a unique node or
a single node which does not have a parent.
And if you look at our particular tree, the
node at the bottom is the only node in this
tree that does not have a parent.
In other words, it does not have an arrow
pointing at it. If it had a parent, then there
would have been other node which had an arrow
pointing at it and I would refer to the new
node as being the parent of this particular
node. But in the node that we have, there
is no such situation and the node which does
not have a parent, the single node in the
tree which does not have a parent is called
the root node. So, I could, we could refer
to it as the root, in general.
So, the kinds of trees that we are talking
about have a single root and then they have
multiple other nodes; each of which has a
parent-child relationship with one of the
other nodes in the tree. In terms of further
terminology, they are, as I said, there are
some of the nodes in the tree which do not
have any children such as this node or in
fact, all of these nodes, none of them has
a child. And this is another node which does
not have a child. So, all of those nodes,
what they have in common is that, they do
not have any children and we would refer to
such nodes as the leaf nodes or the leaves
of the tree.
And once again, in terms of our understanding
of the biological relationship between the
terminology and the tree in nature, the node
at the bottom, in some sense, it is easy to
understand why it is called the root node
because, the tree in nature has roots which
go into the ground and that is why the tree
starts. So, referring to that, the tree, the
node which does not have any parent as the
root node makes a lot of sense. By the same
token, referring to the nodes which are at
the very top and which do not have any more
children as the leaf nodes make sense. Because
there are branches in a biological tree in
nature, but the branches may have leaves on
them. But beyond the leaf, there is nothing
corresponding to a structure belonging to
the tree.
So, the idea of leaf nodes and the root node,
the idea of the tree being made up of nodes
and edges is what we will work with. Now in
practice, when drawing trees in the context
of computer related phenomenon, in other words,
in talking about the use of this kind of a
tree hierarchy in computers, one typically
draws the tree the other way around. In other
words, rather than showing the root at the
bottom and the leaves at the top which is
what one see is a nature, its more often done
to draw the root at the top and the leaves
at the bottom. And once again, this relates
better to our understanding of the use of
hierarchy.
We logically start by looking at something
from the top and since the root that the tree
starts from the root, it makes more sense
to draw the tree having the root at the top.
So, here the analogy with nature sort of breaks
because, one does not in nature, find trees
which have their roots at the top and the
leaves at the bottom. Let us perfectly, we
will continue. From this point on, we will
assume that will see trees which are drawn
in this way; the root at the top and the leaves
lower down. The other nodes of the tree, by
the way, could be referred to as, intermediate
nodes of the tree.
Now, what is the idea of a tree structured
directory hierarchy ? We understand what a
tree is. So, we understand what it means to
be structured like a tree and we see that
the tree is defining some kind of a hierarchy.
But how do the directories enter the picture?
Remember that, the term directories here,
referring to the mechanism that is used by
the operating system, the file system in particular,
to keep track of the mappings between file
names and file descriptors.
So, directory is something which maps file
names to file descriptors. Now, the idea which
would be used in the tree structured directory
hierarchy is that the directories themselves
may be stored on disk, may be similar to the
way that regular files are stored on the disk.
Remember that, a directory has to contain
information. What information it contains;
information about a name to file descriptor
mapping. This is the form of data just like
a file, a text file which you create or program
dot c file that you create contains information
such as the text of a program or at the numbers
that have to be read in by a program.
A directory too contains information. The
information happens to be for each name, the
corresponding file descriptor and this may
not be information that a user program is
going to be is going to used. But it is information
that could be stored in something like a file.
So, that is an interesting idea; the idea
that the directories themselves, in other
words, the mappings between file names and
file descriptors could be stored on disks,
may be very much like regular files. So, what
does the directory file contain? I could refer
to it as a directory file now. The directory
as a file, would now contain pairs of file
names and file descriptors. And here, I am
referring to the file descriptor by the term
index node. You will remember that, in the
case of Unix or Linux, the file descriptor
takes the form of an index and hence the term
index node. So, each of the directories could
contain many filename, index node pairs.
Now, in addition. in the case of the Unix
and Linux type file tree structured directory
hierarchies, each directory contains an entry
with the name dot. So, this is just a dot
and that entry stands for the directory itself.
So, in order for a directory to keep track
of information about itself, given that the
file, the directory itself is something like
a file and entry is maintained within the
directory for itself as well. And that directory,
that entry need not have a name since a directory
itself has a name. But within the directory,
its name is not relevant. Therefore, it is
just represented by an entry with a name dot.
In addition to this, since we are talking
about a tree structured directory hierarchy,
suggestion is that, there would be one node
in the directory hierarchy which is right
at the top and that node is going to be the
root of the directory hierarchy. But other
than that, that need not have a name. And
therefore, in Unix and Linux systems, the
root of the directory hierarchy tree is actually
a nameless directory. And being a nameless
directory, it still has to be referred by
a name.
One cannot just refer to it as the nameless
directory, but it is typically referred to
as the root. Standing for the root of the
directory hierarchy. So,that is actually a
functional name; it has to be the root of
the directory hierarchy. Its name is not root.
in other words, one will not find the name
r o o t root present in a directory referring
to a particular directory. Therefore, in general,
one should understand that the nameless directory
which at the top of the directory hierarchy,
we will refer to it as the root.
Now, what is the hierarchy of directories
that we are talking about? Very clearly, we
are talking about a situation where itself
is a mapping between names and file descriptors
and a directory is stored as a file, something
like a file.
Therefore, there will be an entry for any
particular director in another directory which
happens to have a parent relationship with
a directory that we are talking about. Hence
this notion of a directory hierarchy that
have directory which contains an entry for
another directories name, in turn the directory,
the second directory could have an entry for
another directories and hence there is a tree
structured relationship between the different
directories.
So, what this boils down to then is, in order
to refer to any particular file by name, one
could actually start with the root directory,
the nameless directory at the very root of
the entire directory hierarchy and then go
down the different directories until one comes
to the file that one is referring to, and
the pathway through which one goes through
the directory hierarchy could be referred
to as the pathname of the file.
The file itself would be a leaf node in the
directory hierarchy. Let us just look at an
example to understand what this means. Typically,
in constructing the pathname, one separates
the sequence of directories by slashes and
so, I would refer to a pathname is being a
slash separated sequence of directory names.
Remember, we talke about a directory is having
a name, simply because a directory itself
stored on a disk like a regular file and must
therefore have a name other than of course,
special nameless directory which is called
the root.
So, going back to a picture of a tree, let
us try to understand how this could relate
to a directory hierarchy. Now, the situation
that we should have here is, we should clearly
understand that each of the nodes in this
tree is going to correspond to a file.
Now, some of these nodes are going to correspond
to files that are in fact directories, in
other words, files that contain mapping is
between names and file descriptors or I node
numbers. Some of the other files in the hierarchy
are going to be files containing data that
user can use. And as you would imagine, any
of the intermediate nodes in the directory
is going to be a directory in that. I am sorry,
any intermediate node in the hierarchy it
is going to be a directory and it is the leaf
nodes in this hierarchy which are going to
be the data containing files. So, if I associated
a name with everyone of these nodes and I
am using simple names just for ease of a typing,
this particular node, I am calling node a.
Remember, every file could be a data containing
file or it could be directory, must have a
name.
So, the name of this particular file is a.
I have used names going form a to o for this
particular example. At the top, we have that
special nameless node of the directory hierarchy
tree which is why I do not have a name associated
with it. But we will refer, we have to have
a name to refer to it in discussing it. So,
I will just include the word root there. But
just note that, that is not the name of that
node, it just happens to be what we call that
node. Hence, I have put it in italicize font.
It is not technically a name associated with
that node, it is just what we are going to
refer to that node as. So, let us just consider,
the directory corresponding to that root node.
Remember what I mean by a directory; this
is something like a file and what that file
contains is mapping between file names or
directory names and file descriptors.
So, let us look at the directory corresponding
to the root node. What would we expect to
see in that directory. We might expect to
see something like this. So, it is a file
or its it is a short on disk and contains
information and the information happens to
be in the form of pairs of names and file
descriptors or file descriptor numbers in
this case.
So, the file descriptors themselves may be
stored somewhere else and these are referring
to the names or the numbers of the corresponding
file descriptor. So, in this particular directory,
we find out that there is an entry for each
of the files or directories which is in the
next level of the hierarchy. So, there is
an entry for a. There is an entry for b and
there is an entry for c. And the entry corresponds,
the corresponding entry contains the name
of that file or directory, as well as information
about where that file or directory is contained
on the disk in the form of the number of the
index node corresponding to that file. In
addition on the previous slide, every directory
will contain an entry called dot for itself.
So, the entry called dot will correspond to
the root directory and it tells me that, the
information containing the root directory
is contained in index node number 13. Therefore,
the actual information about where this information
is contained is available in index node number
13.
So, this is the idea of the tree structured
directory hierarchy and just to make sure
we understand what the pathname is, if you
refer to, let say the file down at the bottom
which I called o; file o down at the bottom,
then if I try to trace its complete path from
the root directory, then I would say that,
if at the root directory, I had to take the
branch going through c.From c, I had to take
the branch going to h; I separate the branches
by slashes and from h, I have to take a branch
which takes me to o.
I started this whole thing from root which
is a nameless directory. So, there is nothing
before the first slash. In order to go to
this particular file, I look into the root
directory, I find the entry called c which
tells me that, the information relating to
this particular file must be further persued
in the directory called c.
So, I open up the directory called c. If I
am trying to find out the information about
where the disk blocks of the file o are contained,
I open up the file called c and look into
that for another entry relating to the directory
h and so on. It is the pretty much what the
file system has to do. And this provides a
mechanism through which, complete pathnames
can be used to identify files, starting from
the unique root directory. Now, there are
many possibilities as to how this could be
used. For example, the person who is administering
your system might provide different users
with directories at the second level. So,
a might be the first user, b might be the
second user and c might be the third user.
Subsequently, each of the users could create
their own subdirectories. In other words,
within their region of the directory hierarchy,
they can create directories to their liking.
For example, user b may have created a subdirectory
called f and a subdirectory called g, corresponding
may be to the two courses that that user is
doing. And in each of these two subdirectories,
I could be a file and the two files could
actually have same both of these files. I
have called 1 l and I have called 1 m.
But both of them could just as well have been
called program dot c. How would the operating
system differ between these two program dot
c is by the fact that, one of them has a pathname,
slash b slash f slash program dot c; that
is this one. And the other one has a pathname,
slash b slash g slash program dot c. So, even
though both of the files they seem to have
the name program dot c, they are unique in
that if I look at the entire pathname. The
pathnames are different. And with this mechanism,
it is possible for many of the problems that
we saw with a two earlier directory hierarchy
ideas,I am sorry,the directory ideas to be
overcome.
So, this is a commonly used idea in Unix and
Linux style maintenance of directory information
in Unixand Linux. Now, with this, we have
seen pretty much what is happening in Unix
and Linux systems from disk management. The
idea of the indexed allocation using a fixed
size index node, we have seen that there is
the idea of the tree structured directory
hierarchy and the important concept of pathnames
and how there could be directories which contain
information about the mapping between file
names and file descriptors.
And just as a small aside, I should mention
that, now that we know that directories are
stored on disk very much like files, it may
be interesting to try and see whether, you
as a user, can open a directory just as you
can open a file, whether you can open a directory
and read the contents of the directory. It
might be too much to expect to be able to
modify the contents of the directory. But
it may be possible for you to try to write
the program that tries to open a directory
and read the contents of the directory. And
if you can do this, then you should be able
to write a program, such as the l s program
that we heard about, one or two lectures ago.
What the l s program does is, it produces
a listing of the contents of the current directory
Therefore, it should be conceivable to write
such an l s program, if one can open a directory
and readout its contents and just print them
out on the screen. Now, we can now move on
to the third important aspect of file system
design. And that relates to protection. And
specifically, by talking about what mechanisms
are available to protect files from users;
to protect the files of one user from another
user.
Now, why it does one need to protect the files
of one user from another user? Now, the reason
that one is to do this is to prevent any misuse
of the files within the file system and the
misuse could be accidental or could be intentional.
But I mean by accidental is, if I, as a user,
and I am able to access files of yours, then
I could accidentally delete such a file. Many
of you are familiar with the Unix r m command
to remove a file and some of you may even
have been in the situation where you accidentally
removed one of your own files by just typing
r m on the file.
Now, things could be even worse if I could
accidentally remove files of other users.
Similarly, there is a danger that there could
be some intentional attempt to misuse files.
Example, to either steal the contents of somebody's
file, misuse them in that form or to modify
the contents of somebody else file and this
is clearly something that a file system should
be designed to prevent.
Now, any protection mechanism will have a
few common aspects to it. I am going to talk
about each of these aspects a little bit.
The first thing is, we have this clear understanding
that, we are going to associate a file with
a user and one talks about a file belonging
to a user. Hence, the first step in any kind
of a protection mechanism must be to identify
or to figure out who a particular user is.
When a program is being run, one assumes that
the program is associated with a particular
user.
But the operating system must somehow associate
the execution of the program with a particular
user and must make sure that, the programmers
in fact, started or the execution of that
program was initiated by that particular user.
Therefore there is a need to do something
called user identification or authentication.
Actually, verifying that the user claiming
to be, let say, user one is in fact, user
one. Now, essentially the objective of authentication
is to establish that the user is, whoever
he or she claims to be. If one did not have
user authentication then, a person could just
come to a computer system and start claiming
to be the administrator of the system and
do all kinds of things on the system. Therefore,
authentication is very clearly an important
part of any protection mechanism.
Now, you may ask how could authentication
be done and some of you will be familiar with
one of the commonly used mechanisms for authentication;
and that is the use of user ids and passwords.
So, the idea here is that, whenever a new
account is created for a user, the user is
asked to provide a password,password code
that will be remembered by the computer system
and used by the user; in return, the user
tries to log in to the computer system. Subsequently,
when the user does login to the computer system,
you will be, he or she will be asked to provide
the user id as well as the password. And the
computer system can then verify. The computer
system will have to store the passwords securely.
But the computer system can then check whether
the password has typed in by the user is the
same as the password as remembered in the
computer system. If they match, this can be
used as confirmation that the user is who
he or she claims to be. Now, it is of course
important that, the passwords be stored securely.
You will note that the passwords himself will
probably have to be stored in a file. They
cannot be stored in main memory. Because they
must survive beyond the life time of one program.
And if that is going to be stored in a file
in a haphazard way, then any of the users
currently on the system would be able to open
and read the password file and therefore,
all the passwords would then become common
knowledge and so on.
So very clearly, some mechanisms for making
sure that the passwords are stored securely
will have to be ensured such as encryption
or something along those lines. Now, there
are other more recently, there have been other
different kinds of ideas for doing user authentication
based on other ideas other than password.
And you may have heard of some of these which
are known as biometrics. For example, many
of the laptops that you may be using, may
actually have mechanisms through which one
can record and display ones fingerprint and
fingerprint information could actually be
used for authentication. If this kind of a
biometric is used for authentication, then
when you attempt to login into the computer
system, you would be asked to put your, one
of the finger which fingerprint had been recorded,
onto the fingerprint reader, on the on that
laptop.
It would be then compared with the stored
version of your fingerprint and if there was
adequate correspondence, this would be viewed
as authenticating you as the user who you
claim to be. So, this is similar to the password,
in that there, it is a secret stored on the
computer and available only to the user. But
unlike the password which is something that
one has to remember, the fingerprint is biological
reality as far as the individual is concerned
and very difficult for somebody else to replicate.
Other ideas which are use today are based
on the iris. The iris of the eye and iris
device which could be used to check the iris
properties of the individual who is currently
trying to login to the computer system, compare
those with these stored facts known about
the iris properties of that particular user
and using this for authentication.
So, this of course is important to note that,
if passwords are being used, one must of course,
make sure that, the ones password is adequate
strength, in order to make it difficult for
other users or people who are trying to break
into a system to misuse ones user id by guessing
ones password. So, user of the, authentication
and identification of the users is an important
property of any protection mechanism.
Now, in other important aspect as far as find
the system protection is concerned is what
is called authorization determination. And
the problem here is, of the many users on
the computer system, for a particular file
that we are interested in, we have to track;
the operating system to keep track of what
the different users or what a particular users
is entitled to do as far as a particular file
is concerned. And that is what we might refer
to as determining what the user is authorized
to do in connection with a particular file.
Now, this itself may seem like a trivial problem.
But if you think about it a little bit, you
will realize that, in order to do this, the
system, operating system, the file system
will have to keep track of what kinds of operations
each user do for each file and therefore,
the amount of information that would have
to be stored in connection with authorization
determination could be substantial. Remember
that, authorization information would have
to be stored for each file. First of all,
it will have to be stored for each user, but
it will have to be stored for each file and
there could be thousands, millions of files
on a computer system. For each of those files,
information about what privilege, what operations
each user could do on that file must be stored.
So, for each of the million files on a computer
system, there would have to be information
about each of the thousand users on the computer
system, it leaving us with a huge amount of
information that would have to be stored.
And therefore,this is not a trivial problem,
it is a problem of a sizable dimensions in
terms of the amount of information that might
have to be stored unless it is dealt with,
in a careful fashion.
Now, the way that authorization information
is stored in the case of the Unix and Linux
styles systems is interesting and therefore
I will go through that. The idea here is,
rather than storing information about how
each of thousands of users would be able to,
at the different operations, each of thousands
of users would be allowed to do on each of
millions of files. Unix or Linux manages with
just nine bits of information and the way
that it does this, is by first of all, not
maintaining information about each user for
each file, by dividing the universe of users
into three sets in connection with the given
file. The three sets are first of all, the
owner of the file and we understand now that,
associated with each file, there is going
to be a particular user who is considered
to be the owner of the file. Second group,
the second set of users that the operating
system maintains information about is the
associates of the owner of the file. In other
words, the other users on the system who associate
with and collaborate with or interact with
the owner of the file and this is typically
referred to as the users who are in the same
group as the owner of the file.
The keyword there is group. The keyword in
the first grouping was owner,the keyword in
the second grouping is group and the third,
a set of users that the operating system maintains
information about, in connection with each
file, is what is known as the other users
or other. So there is owner, there is group
and there is others. So, the operating system
does not maintain information on the basis
of each of the thousand users, the operating
system just maintains information on the basis
of these three groupings.
One set of information for the owner of the
file, an other set of information use, as
in, the group as the file as the owner of
the file and third set of information for
everyone else. What about the actual permission,
the actual operations that the user would
be allow to do on a particular file. The way
that Unix or Linux maintains this information
is by distinguishing between three kinds of
operations; the read operation, the write
operation and the execute operation. Now,
you will remember here that, we are talking
about operations on files and we clearly understand
that it may be necessary to read data from
a file. It may be necessary to write data
from a file and to write data to a file. And
hence, these are clearly well specified operations
that we can relate to. But this whole notion
of having an execute operation on a file is
new.
Up to now, we were thinking a files as being
data containing, but we should bear in mind
that, some of the files that are present on
a computer system such as an a dot out file
will typically not be opened and read or written
by a user. On the other hand, they are more
likely to be executed by a user. And therefore,
the execution or running a program has to
be viewed as being an operation and hence
in Unix and Linux systems, there is a separate,
a third operation for which authorization
bits are kept track of, known as the execute
operation.
So, when we put all this together, then figure
out that, what the Unix linux is doing is
that associated with any one file, it is maintaining
nine bits of information; three of the bits
of information relate to the permissions or
the operations that the owner of the file
can do on the file, three of the bits of information
relate to the operations that in group, as
the owner, can do on that particular file
and the last three bits of information relate
to the kinds of operations that any other
user on the system could do to that particular
file. Here, we are talking about the file,
a dot out for example. What are the three
bits? The three bits are permission to read,
write or execute the file which are typically
indicated by r w and x.
So, for a particular file, if the owner has
the permission to read or write or execute
the file, one would find those three bits
set in the collection of information that
the operating system is maintaining about
that particular file. If the members of the
same group as the owner are allowed to read
the file, but not to execute, or to write
it, then, one might find only the read bit
set and the execute and the write bits not
set. And if the others, the other users on
the system are not allowed to do any operations
on the file, one might not find any of the
others bits set.
So, among the nine bits in this particular
example, we find only the first four bits
are set. The other five bits are not set and
subsequently, the operating system could use
this storage of authorization information
relating to the file a dot out, in allowing
or not allowing any particular access.
Now, there are certain other niceties of this
which one could think about. For example,
in addition to the fact that some files contain
data, and other files are executable, we have
this additional complication from our discussion
of name management. Some of the files in a
computer system are actually directories.
For example, there is a root directory, there
are subdirectories associate with each user
and so on. And a directory is essentially,
as we see something like a file, but contains
information about the location of other files.
But a directory in itself, will have to have
these protection bits associated with it.
So, there will be the idea of the owner of
a directory and the operations that in owner
could do on a file which are going to be represented
by the read write and execute bits; just as
for any other file and one could interpret
or try to understand with the operating system
means by reading a directory, writing a directory
or executing a directory. It make sense to
view reading a directory as being able to
open and access the entries in the directory.
So, for example, in order to execute the l
s command, one would have to have read permission
on the corresponding directory. Typically,
when one talks about writing as referring
to modifying the contents of a file, in connection
with a directory, therefore one must assume
that one would require the write permission
if one was going to modify the contents of
a directory. Now, one would modify the contents
of the directory, if one needed to remove
a directory entry or to add a new directory
entry and therefore to do either of these
operations, it may be necessary to have the
write permission on a directory. Similarly,
for execute, one could argue what the meaning
of the execute permission might have on a
directory and so on.
So, with this, we understand that, while,
in order to specify the different authorizations
that millions of, on millions of files by
thousands of users in the first case, it look
like a huge amount of information might have
to be remembered. With this simple scheme,
unix systems are able to manage with just
nine bits of information for each file in
the file system.
So subsequently, once the information about
what operations can be done by each class
of users on a particular file, the next question
is how is this going to be enforced. So, the
access enforcement. The first issue in protection
mechanism was authenticating the users, the
second issue was actually having track of
the information about what operations each
user could do on each file. The third aspect
is enforcing those authorizations, making
sure that the user who does not have permission
to read a file, does not when that user attempts
to write a program that does read the file,
making sure that the access is not allowed.
So, that is the objective of access enforcement.
And as you can well imagine, this is the important
final step of the protection problem and it
involves preventing users from doing unauthorized
accesses to files and would clearly involve
whenever user attempts to open a file to do,
let us say, read access, the operating system
is checking to make sure that, this particular
user with that particular user id has the
permissions and this can be done by referring
to the access bits, the nine access bits associated
with the file.
Now, one piece of information which I did
not mention, I talked about these nine bits
of information with a file and the question
will of course, arise to where the nine bits
of information be stored. You will recall
that, associated with each file, there is
a directory entry and the directory entry
contains a mapping between the file name.
So, directory entry contains mapping between
the file name and the I node number. For example,
might be I node number thirteen, the file
descriptor, the I node which contains the
information about that location of the different
data blocks of the file. Where then are the
read, write, execute the nine bit stored as
far as file a dot out is concerned? Where
is the information about who the owner of
the file a dot out is concerned is stored?
Now, when we talked about the directory, clearly
said that, directory was the mapping between
file names and file descriptors. I never said
that, the directory contains other information.
And there may well be reasons for not wanting
to put additional information inside the file
directory. Because, as we have, as I have
suggested, a directory is like a file on the
disk and can actually be opened by any user
who has read permission to the directory and
the contents of the directory can be read.
Therefore, it is probably not a good idea
for the operating system to keep a lot of
additional information inside the directory.
Where then, is this additional information
contain and the additional information that
I am talking about are the read write execute
bits associated with that file, as well as
information such as, who is the owner of the
file, who are the members of the group associated
with that file and so on. So, there are lot
of other pieces of information associated
with a file, then operating system will have
to keep track off .And as far as much of this
information is concerned, the information
will in fact, be stored inside the structured,
which until no,w I have been calling - the
I node,the index node. So, the index node,
in addition to containing the index corresponding
to the file, will also contain other information
conceivably the read write execute permissions
permission bits on the file, as well as information
about who the owner of the file is and there
could be other piece of information such as
the date and time on which the file was created,
the date and time at which the file was last
modified and there is other information that
might be relevant as far as a file is concerned.
So, all of this additional information about
a file will typically not be stored in the
directory. But will actually be stored inside
the I node or the index node, corresponding
to the file. And the index node contains the
index, in addition to all this information.
We understand why it is called the index node
rather than being referred as to the index.
Now, putting all this together, we realize
that, as far as the operating system is concerned,
the disk contains a lot of information. Let
me just draw the disk over here, we have a
perspective of the disk as being linearly
addressed from disk block 0 up to some maximum
disk block address and parts of the disk are
used for the file system. So, there could
be regions of the disk which contains the
blocks of the different files.
But in addition to this, there is a lot of
information regarding the file system such
as, all the I nodes that also will have to
be stored on the disk. Therefore, we suspect
that parts of the disk are going to be reserved
by the operating system for things like remembering
the I nodes of all the files which are stored
inside the file system. And once we learn
a little bit more about the way that the disk
is used, we would have been able to understand
how to access the I nodes.
Now, one final comment on these, the aspect
of protection. I have talked about how one
could imagine writing an l s program. l s
program is the program which you invoke l
s and it will list on the screen, the contents
that the names of the various files which
are present in the directory- the current
directory. And I suggested that, this could
be done by opening the directory as a file
and reading and writing its contents. But
we now understand that, the contents of the
directory include the name of the file, but
a lot of the information that we know, the
l s program is capable of giving to us is
not contained in the directory itself. It
is actually contained inside the index node
or the I node,corresponding to the file. And
therefore, writing the l s program may require
a little bit more information that what we
actually have at this point in time.
Now, with this comments, I will close our
discussion of the fundamental issues in file
system design. And in the next lecture, we
will move on to another and very important
topic from the perspective of our programming,
that is file system performance.
Now, we understand that the files are all
stored on disk and that we have programs which
will access the files by opening them, reading
the contents of the file. Therefore, we would
like to know something more about files from
the perspective of understanding how we can
make our programs which access files more
efficient in terms of time. We will show in
the next lecture. Thank you.