dear friends we are going to look into
numpy by module today it is extremely
popular in Python community and it is
heavily used for scientific computing we
will see why it is so popular so let's
first start by installing it I will
install it using pip you can run pip
install numpy white come on to download
and install it while it is installing
numpy wise main object is n dimensional
array okay so we will look into that
array so here I have my Python Idol
shall open and I'm going to import numpy
Y model here so num I've imported it as
NP and to create an array object you
will use NP dot array and in this
bracket you just pass down your list so
this is my num P Y array if you look
into it now this is sort of similar to a
list it is actually very similar to a
list you can access the elements by
index it looks like a list so the
question is I only have a list why do I
need this number by array well there are
several benefits of using numpy array.